Finding Aid for William Walter Wedemeyer papers, 1890-1913
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Walter Wedemeyer papers 1890-1913
Wedemeyer, William Walter, 1873-1913.
1.3 linear feet (in 2 boxes)
86253 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan attorney, American consul in British Guiana in 1905, and U.S. Congressman, 1911-1913. Political and business correspondence, notes and addresses, and other materials relating to his business interests and political career; also papers concerning his trips to Alaska, British Guiana, and Panama.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Wedemeyer family (donor no. 1398 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William Walter Wedemeyer was born near Lima Township, Washtenaw County, Mich., March 22, 1873. He graduated from the law department of the University of Michigan in 1895. He began his political and public service career as a member of the board of school examiners in 1894 and 1895, as county commissioner of schools 1895-1897, and as deputy commissioner of railroads for Michigan 1897-1899. Active in the Republican Party, Wedemeyer was chairman of the Republican State convention in 1903 and a member of the Republican State Central Committee 1906-1910. He was elected to the Sixty-second Congress in 1910. He served most of one term. He was defeated in his campaign for reelection in 1912 and died near the end of his term while on an official visit to Colon, Panama, on January 2, 1913.
The Wedemeyer collection includes political and business correspondence, notes and addresses, and other materials relating to his business interests and political career. There are also papers concerning his trips to Alaska, British Guiana, and Panama. Some of his correspondents included Russell A. Alger, James B. Angell, Gerrit J. Diekema, Frederick Douglass, Benjamin Harrison, Frank Knox, Charles E. Townsend, James Schermerhorn, Henry C. Smith, and Fred M. Warner.
Subjects:
Alaska--Description and travel.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Chelsea (Mich.); Guyana--Description and travel.; Panama--Description and travel.; Republican Party (Mich.); South America.; Voyages and travels.; United States--Politics and government--1909-1913.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1909.
Contributors:
Alger, R. A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Diekema, Gerrit John, 1859-1930.; Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Schermerhorn, James, 1865-1942.; Smith, Henry Cassorte, 1859-1911.; Townsend, Charles Elroy, 1856-1924.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.
- Correspondence
  - 1890, 1893 and 1899-1900 (Box 1)
    (include letters, 1893, from Frederick Douglass and Benjamin Harrison)
  - 1901-1905 (Box 1)
    (include letters from Russell A. Alger, Gerrit J. Diekema, Charles E. Townsend, and Fred M. Warner)
  - 1907, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1908-1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910 (Box 1)
    (include letter from Charles E. Townsend)
  - 1911, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (include letter from James Schermerhorn and Frank Knox)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    (include letter from James B. Angell)
- Other materials
  - Press notices and campaign statements (Box 1)
  - Speeches, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes and addresses on
    - Alaskan trip (Box 1)
    - Panama (Box 1)
    - Michigan topics (Box 1)
    - Abraham Lincoln (Box 1)
    - Notes and address given to the American Insurance Union (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes and addresses (Box 1)
  - Political speeches, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes, outline, and text of commencement address at Ohio Northern University (Box 1)
  - Notes and addresses on trip to South America (Box 1)
  - Address given while member of the House of Representatives (Box 2)
  - Legal briefs (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning the Chelsea State Bank and the Glazier Stove Company, 1907 and undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)